The future, as we know it, is very unpredictable.
المستقبل ، كما نعلمه ، صعب التنبؤ به جداً .
The best minds in the best institutions
أفضل العقول في أفضل المؤسسات
generally get it wrong.
تخطئ عموما .
This is in technology. This is in the area of politics,
هذا في التكنولوجيا . هذا في مجال السياسة ،
where pundits, the CIA, MI6 always get it wrong.
حيث النقاد ، CIA, MI6، دائماً يخطئون.
And it's clearly in the area of finance.
ومن الواضح في قطاع المال.
With institutions established to think about the future,
مع وجود مؤسسات أقيمت للتفكير حول المستقبل،
the IMF, the BIS, the Financial Stability Forum, couldn't see what was coming.
IMF, BIS, منتدى الإستقرار المالي، لم يستطيعوا معرفة الشئ القادم.
Over 20,000 economists
أكثر من 20 ألف إقتصادي
whose job it is, competitive entry to get there,
الذين ينحصر عملهم في ، المنافسة للدخول الى هناك ،
couldn't see what was happening.
لم يستطيعوا معرفة ماذا يحدث .
Globalization is getting more complex.
العولمة تصبح أكثر تعقيداً .
And this change is getting more rapid.
وهذا التغيير يصبح أكثر سرعةً .
The future will be more unpredictable.
المستقبل سيكون أكثر صعوبة للتنبؤ .
Urbanization, integration,
التحضّر، التكامل ،
coming together, leads to a new renaissance.
يأتيان معاً ، يقودان إلى نهضة جديدة .
It did this a thousand years ago.
لقد فعلت هذا قبل آلالاف السنين مضت .
The last 40 years have been extraordinary times.
الأربعون سنة الماضية كانت أزمنة غير عادية.
Life expectancy has gone up by about 25 years.
إرتفع متوسط العمر المتوقع بحوالي 25 عاما .
It took from the Stone Age to achieve that.
إستغرق الأمر من العصر الحجري لتحقيق ذلك .
Income has gone up for a majority of the world's population,
إرتفعت الدخول لغالبية سكان العالم ،
despite the population going up by about two billion people over this period.
بالرغم من زيادة السكان بحوالي بليوني شخص في نفس هذه الفترة .
And illiteracy has gone down, from a half to about a quarter of the people on Earth.
وإنخفضت الأميّة ، من النصف الى ربع السكان على الأرض .
A huge opportunity, unleashing of new potential
فرصة عظيمة ، لتفجير الطاقات الجديدة
for innovation, for development.
للإبتكار، للتنمية .
But there is an underbelly.
لكن هناك خفايا .
There are two Achilles' heels of globalization.
هناك أثنين من نقاط الضعف في العولمة .
There is the Achilles' heel of growing inequality --
هناك نقطة ضعف في انعدام المساواة المتزايد.
those that are left out, those that feel angry,
لإؤلئك المتروكين ، لإؤلئك الغاضبين ،
those that are not participating. Globalization
أؤلئك الذين لا يشاركون . العولمة
has not been inclusive.
لم تكن شاملة.
The second Achilles' heel is complexity --
نقطة الضعف الأخرى هي التعقيد .
a growing fragility, a growing brittleness.
هشاشة متنامية ، وحشية متنامية .
What happens in one place very quickly affects everything else.
ما يحدث في مكان ما يؤثر بسرعة كبيرة في أماكن آخري .
This is a systemic risk, systemic shock.
هذه هي المخاطر النظامية ، وصدمة منظمة .
We've seen it in the financial crisis. We've seen it in the pandemic flu.
لقد شهدنا الأزمة المالية . شهدنا وباء الإنفلونزا .
It will become virulent and it's something we have to build resilience against.
سوف تصبح خبيثة وهي شئ يجب أن نبني قدرة لمواجهتها .
A lot of this is driven by what's happening in technology.
الكثير من هذا يحركه ما يحدث في التكنولوجيا .
There have been huge leaps. There will be a million-fold improvement
كانت هناك قفزات ضخمة . سيكون هناك مليون متغير للتحسن
in what you can get for the same price
في ما تستطيع شراءه بنفس السعر
in computing by 2030.
في توقعاتنا عام 2030 .
That's what the experience of the last 20 years has been.
هذا ما كانت عليه تجربة العشرين سنة الماضية .
It will continue.
ستتواصل .
Our computers, our systems will be as primitive
حواسيبنا ، أنظمتنا ستصبح بدائية
as the Apollo's are for today.
كما هو حال أبولو اليوم .
Our mobile phones are more powerful than the total Apollo space engine.
هواتفنا المحمولة أكثر قوة من محرك مركبة الفضاء أبولو .
Our mobile phones are more powerful than
هواتفنا المحمول أكثر قوة من
some of the strongest computers of 20 years ago.
بعض أقوى الحواسيب خلال عشرين سنة مضت .
So what will this do?
إذا ماذا سيفعل هذا ؟
It will create huge opportunities in technology.
سيخلق فرصة ضخمة في التكنولوجيا .
Miniaturization as well.
وكذلك التصغير .
There will be invisible capacity. Invisible capacity in our bodies,
ستكون هناك إمكانية غير مرئية . إمكانية كامنة في أجسادنا ،
in our brains, and in the air.
في عقولنا ، وفي الهواء .
This is a dust mite on a nanoreplica.
هذا هو عث الغبار على جزيئ نانو .
This sort of ability to do everything in new ways unleashes potential,
هذا النوع من المقدرة لفعل أي شئ بوسائل حديثة مطلق لها العنان ،
not least in the area of medicine.
ليس أقلها في مجال الطب.
This is a stem cell that we've developed here in Oxford,
هذه الخلية الجذعية التي طورّناها هنا في أوكسفورد،
from an embryonic stem cell.
من خلايا جذعية جنينية .
We can develop any part of the body.
يمكننا تطوير أي جزء من الجسم .
Increasingly, over time, this will be possible from our own skin --
وبإضطراد ، بمرور الوقت ، سيكون هذا ممكناً من جلودنا نفسها --
able to replicate parts of the body.
تقدر على تبديل بعض أجزاء الجسم .
Fantastic potential for regenerative medicine.
قابلية هائلة للطب التجديدي .
I don't think there will be a Special Olympics long after 2030,
لا أعتقد أنه سيكون هناك أولمبياد مميزة لفترة طويلة بعد 2030 ،
because of this capacity to regenerate parts of the body.
بسبب هذه الإمكانية لإعادة تجديد أجزاء من الجسم .
But the question is, "Who will have it?"
لكن السؤال هو ، " من سيحصل عليها ؟ "
The other major development is going to be
التطور الرئيسي الآخر سيكون
in the area of what can happen in genetics.
في مجال ما يمكن أن يحدث في علم الجينات .
The capacity to create, as this mouse has been genetically modified,
إمكانية تخليق ، مثل أن تكون هذه الفأرة معدلة جينياً ،
something which goes three times faster,
شيئ ما يستطيع المشي أسرع ثلاث مرات ،
lasts for three times longer, we could produce,
يعيش ثلاثة أضعاف العمر ، نستطيع إن ننتجه ،
as this mouse can, to the age of our equivalent of 80 years,
كما يستطيع هذا الفأر، العيش لعمر يكافئ 80 عاماً ،
using about the same amount of food.
يستخدم حوالي نفس كمية الغذاء .
But will this only be available for the super rich,
ولكن هل هذا لن يكون متاحا إلا للأثرياء ,
for those that can afford it? Are we headed for a new eugenics?
لإؤلئك الذين يقدرون على الدفع ؟ هل نحن نمضي تجاه تحديد جيل جديد ؟
Will only those that are able to afford it
هل فقط أؤلئك الذين يقدرون على تكلفتها
be able to be this super race of the future?
سيقدرون على أن يكونوا السباق الأعظم للمستقبل ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the big question for us is,
إذاً السؤال الكبير الموجه لنا هو،
"How do we manage this technological change?"
" كيف نتدبر هذا التغيير التكنولوجي ؟ "
How do we ensure that it creates
كيف يمكننا أن نضمن أنه يصنع
a more inclusive technology,
تكنولوجيا أكثر شمولا ،
a technology which means
التكنولوجيا التي تعني
that not only as we grow older,
ليس فقط كلما نكبر ،
that we can also grow wiser, and that we're able to support
تزيد حكمتنا بل أيضا أن نكون قادرين على دعم
the populations of the future?
سكان المستقبل ؟
One of the most dramatic manifestations of these improvements
أحد المظاهر الأكثر إثارةً لهذه التحسينات
will be moving from population pyramids
ستكون الإنتقال من هرمية السكان ،
to what we might term population coffins.
لما يمكن أن نسميه التوابيت السكانية .
There is unlikely to be a pension
لا يرجح أن تكون هناك معاش
or a retirement age in 2030.
أو سن تقاعد عام 2030 .
These will be redundant concepts. And this isn't only something of the West.
ستكون هذه مفاهيم بالية . وهذا ليس شيئاً فقط في الغرب .
The most dramatic changes will be the skyscraper
التغيير الأكثر إثارةً سيكون ناطحات السحاب
type of new pyramids
ذات الشكل الهرمي ،
that will take place in China and in many other countries.
التي سيتم تشييدها في الصين والعديد من البلدان الأخرى .
So forget about retirements if you're young.
لذا أنسوا موضوع التقاعد إذا كنتم شباب .
Forget about pensions. Think about life and where it's going to be going.
أنسوا موضوع المعاش . فكروا في الحياة وإلى أين ستتجه .
Of course, migration will become even more important.
بالطبع ، الهجرة ستصبح أكثر أهمية .
The war on talent, the need to attract people
الحرب على المواهب ، الحاجة لجذب الناس
at all skill ranges,
في كل مستويات المهارة ،
to push us around in our wheelchairs,
لتدفعنا على مقعدنا المتحرك في الجوار ،
but also to drive our economies. Our innovation will be vital.
وأيضاً لتحريك إقتصاداتنا . إبتكاراتنا ستكون أمراً حيويا .
The employment in the rich countries
والعمالة في الدول الغنية
will go down from about 800
ستنخفض من حوالي 800
to about 700 million of these people.
الى حوالي 700 مليون من هؤلاء الناس .
This would imply a massive leap in migration.
وهذا يعني قفزة هائلة في مجال الهجرة .
So the concerns, the xenophobic concerns of today,
حتى المخاوف ، المخاوف العادية لليوم ،
of migration, will be turned on their head,
بالنسبة للهجرة ، ستنقلب علي رؤوسهم ،
as we search for people to help us sort out
لأننا نبحث عن أناس يساعدونا نوعا ما
our pensions and our economies in the future.
لمساعدتنا في فرز معاشنا واقتصاداتنا في المستقبل .
And then, the systemic risks.
و من ثم ، المخاطر المنتظمة.
We understand that these will become much more virulent,
نحن نفهم أن هذه ستصبح أكثر ضراوة ،
that what we see today
عن ما نراه اليوم ،
is this interweaving of societies, of systems,
هي هذه المجتمعات المتشابكة ، للأنظمة ،
fastened by technologies and hastened by just-in-time management systems.
تتسارع بالتكنولوجيات ، وتعجل بأنظمة إدارة فورية .
Small levels of stock push resilience into other people's responsibility.
مستويات صغيرة من المخزون تحث علي النهضة إلى مسئولية الآخرين .
The collapse in biodiversity,
الإنهيار في تنوع كافة أشكال الحياه ،
climate change, pandemics, financial crises:
تغير المناخ ، الأوبئة ، الأزمة المالية :
these will be the currency that we will think about.
ستكون هي العملة التي سنفكر بها .
And so a new awareness will have to arise,
ولذا يجب أن يظهر نوع جديد من الوعي ،
of how we deal with these, how we mobilize ourselves,
حول كيفية التعامل معها ، كيف نعبئ أنفسنا ،
in a new way, and come together as a community
بطريقة جديدة ، ونتوحد سوياً كمجتمع
to manage systemic risk.
لإدارة الأخطار المحتملة .
It's going to require innovation.
إن الأمر سيتطلب الإبتكار .
It's going to require an understanding that the glory of globalization
سيتطلب الأمر فهما بأن مجد العولمة
could also be its downfall.
قد يكون أيضاً منزلقا .
This could be our best century ever because of the achievements,
قد يكون هذا أفضل قرن لنا بسبب الإنجازات .
or it could be our worst.
أو يمكن أن يكون الأسوأ .
And of course we need to worry about the individuals,
وبالطبع نحتاج لأن نقلق بشأن الأفراد .
particularly the individuals that feel that they've
تحديداً الأفراد الذين يشعرون بأنهم
been left out in one way or another.
تم إهمالهم ، بطريقة أو بأخرى .
An individual, for the first time in the history of humanity,
الفرد ولأول مرة ، في تاريخ البشرية ،
will have the capacity, by 2030,
سيحصل على القدرة ، بحلول عام 2030 ,
to destroy the planet, to wreck everything,
لتدمير الكوكب ، لتدمير كل شئ ,
through the creation, for example, of a biopathogen.
عبر التخليق ، على سبيل المثال ، الأمراض الحيوية .
How do we begin to weave these tapestries together?
كيف يمكن لنا أن نبدأ في التحرك و رسم هذه اللوحات معاً ؟
How do we think about complex systems in new ways?
كيف يمكننا التفكير حول تعقيد الأنظمة بطريقة حديثة ؟
That will be the challenge of the scholars,
سيكون ذلك تحدياً للعلماء ،
and of all of us engaged in thinking about the future.
وجميعنا ضالعون في التفكير حول المستقبل .
The rest of our lives will be in the future. We need to prepare for it now.
بقية عمرنا سيكون في المستقبل . نحتاج أن نجهّز له الآن .
We need to understand that the governance structure in the world is fossilized.
نحتاج لفهم أن هيكلة الحكم في العالم متحجرة .
It cannot begin to cope with the challenges that this will bring.
لا يستطيع أن يبدأ في التكيف مع التحديات القادمة .
We have to develop a new way of managing the planet,
ينبغي علينا تطوير طريقة جديدة لإدارة الكوكب ،
collectively, through collective wisdom.
جماعيا ، عبرحكمة جماعية .
We know, and I know from my own experience,
نحن نعرف ، وأنا أعرف ، من خبرتي الخاصة ،
that amazing things can happen,
أن أشياء رائعة يمكن أن تحدث ،
when individuals and societies come together
عندما يجتمع الأفراد والمجتمعات سوياً
to change their future.
لتغيير مستقبلهم .
I left South Africa, and 15 years later,
لقد غادرت جنوب أفريقيا . وبعد 15 عام لاحقا ،
after thinking I would never go back,
بعد أن إعتقدت أنني لن أرجع إليها البتة ،
I had the privilege and the honor to work in the government of Nelson Mandela.
حصلت على إمتياز و شرف العمل في حكومة نلسون مانديلا .
This was a miracle. We can create miracles,
كانت هذه معجزة . يمكننا صنع المعجزات ،
collectively, in our lifetime.
جماعيا ، في حياتنا .
It is vital that we do so.
فمن الأهمية أن نفعل ذلك .
It is vital that the ideas that are nurtured in TED,
من الأهمية أن الأفكار التي تُنادي بها في تيد
that the ideas that we think about
تلك الأفكار التي نفكر بها ،
look forward, and make sure that this will be the most glorious century,
ننظر إلى المستقبل ، ونتأكد من أن يكون هذا أكثر القرون مجدا ،
and not one of eco-disaster and eco-collapse.
وليس قرن المصائب البيئية ، والإنهيار البيئي .
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم . (تصفيق)